[00:00.34] [Belmont. A room in PORTIA'S house.,]
[00:01.04] [Enter PORTIA, NERISSA, LORENZO, JESSICA, and
[00:01.39] + BALTHASAR]
[00:01.73]LORENZO Madam, although I speak it in your presence,
[00:04.58] You have a noble and a true conceit
[00:07.01] Of godlike amity; which appears most strongly
[00:09.97] In bearing thus the absence of your lord.
[00:14.33] But if you knew to whom you show this honour,
[00:15.41] How true a gentleman you send relief,
[00:17.82] How dear a lover of my lord your husband,
[00:20.11] I know you would be prouder of the work
[00:20.93] Than customary bounty can enforce you.
[00:25.23]PORTIA I never did repent for doing good,
[00:27.37] Nor shall not now: for in companions
[00:29.15] That do converse and waste the time together,
[00:31.37] Whose souls do bear an equal yoke Of love,
[00:34.18] There must be needs a like proportion
[00:37.96] Of lineaments, of manners and of spirit;
[00:39.15] Which makes me think that this Antonio,
[00:42.13] Being the bosom lover of my lord,
[00:43.41] Must needs be like my lord. If it be so,
[00:46.37] How little is the cost I have bestow'd
[00:49.62] In purchasing the semblance of my soul
[00:54.43] From out the state of hellish misery!
[00:56.93] This comes too near the praising of myself;
[00:59.77] Therefore no more of it: hear other things.
[01:02.55] Lorenzo, I commit into your hands
[01:04.81] The husbandry and manage of my house
[01:07.30] Until my lord's return: for mine own part,
[01:10.03] I have toward heaven breathed a secret vow
[01:12.87] To live in prayer and contemplation,
[01:15.30] Only attended by Nerissa here,
[01:17.39] Until her husband and my lord's return:
[01:20.00] There is a monastery two miles off;
[01:22.38] And there will we abide. I do desire you
[01:25.04] Not to deny this imposition;
[01:27.02] The which my love and some necessity
[01:29.51] Now lays upon you.
[01:30.90]LORENZO Madam, with all my heart;
[01:32.64] I shall obey you in all fair commands.
[01:35.19]PORTIA My people do already know my mind,
[01:37.51] And will acknowledge you and Jessica
[01:40.00] In place of Lord Bassanio and myself.
[01:42.49] And so farewell, till we shall meet again.
[01:45.22]LORENZO Fair thoughts and happy hours attend on you!
[01:48.12]JESSICA I wish your ladyship all heart's content.
[01:50.84]PORTIA I thank you for your wish, and am well pleased
[01:53.86] To wish it back on you: fare you well Jessica.
[01:56.81] [Exeunt JESSICA and LORENZO]
[01:57.51] Now, Balthasar,
[01:58.67] As I have ever found thee honest-true,
[02:01.22] So let me find thee still. Take this same letter,
[02:04.35] And use thou all the endeavour of a man
[02:07.02] In speed to Padua: see thou render this
[02:09.63] Into my cousin's hand, Doctor Bellario;
[02:12.18] And, look, what notes and garments he doth give thee,
[02:15.48] Bring them, I pray thee, with imagined speed
[02:18.32] Unto the tranect, to the common ferry
[02:20.82] Which trades to Venice. Waste no time in words,
[02:23.83] But get thee gone: I shall be there before thee.
[02:26.90]BALTHASAR Madam, I go with all convenient speed.
[02:29.40] [Exit]
[02:30.09]PORTIA Come on, Nerissa; I have work in hand
[02:32.53] That you yet know not of: we'll see our husbands
[02:35.66] Before they think of us.
[02:37.40]NERISSA Shall they see us?
[02:38.79]PORTIA They shall, Nerissa; but in such a habit,
[02:41.40] That they shall think we are accomplished
[02:44.18] With that we lack. I'll hold thee any wager,
[02:47.02] When we are both accoutred like young men,
[02:49.80] I'll prove the prettier fellow of the two,
[02:52.59] And wear my dagger with the braver grace,
[02:55.31] And speak between the change of man and boy
[02:58.21] With a reed voice, and turn two mincing steps
[03:01.17] Into a manly stride, and speak of frays
[03:03.77] Like a fine bragging youth, and tell quaint lies,
[03:06.91] How honourable ladies sought my love,
[03:09.40] Which I denying, they fell sick and died;
[03:12.07] I could not do withal; then I'll repent,
[03:14.67] And wish for all that, that I had not killed them;
[03:17.86] And twenty of these puny lies I'll tell,
[03:20.53] That men shall swear I have discontinued school
[03:23.66] Above a twelvemonth. I have within my mind
[03:26.44] A thousand raw tricks of these bragging Jacks,
[03:29.46] Which I will practise.
[03:31.08]NERISSA Why, shall we turn to men?
[03:32.88]PORTIA Fie, what a question's that,
[03:34.79] If thou wert near a lewd interpreter!
[03:37.28] But come, I'll tell thee all my whole device
[03:40.18] When I am in my coach, which stays for us
[03:42.91] At the park gate; and therefore haste away,
[03:45.69] For we must measure twenty miles to-day.
[03:48.36] [Exeunt]
[03:49.00] ./Plays/14-Merchant-of-Venice/14-Merchant-of-Venice-Act-3-Scene-4.mp3 ./Plays/14-Merchant-of-Venice/14-Merchant-of-Venice-Act-3-Scene-4.lrc
