[00:00.39] [Venice. A street.,]
[00:01.19] [Enter LAUNCELOT]
[00:13.03]LAUNCELOT Certainly my conscience will serve me to run from
[00:13.93] this Jew my master. The fiend is at mine elbow and
[00:17.32] tempts me saying to me 'Gobbo, Launcelot Gobbo, good
[00:20.57] Launcelot,' or 'good Gobbo,' or good Launcelot
[00:28.45] Gobbo, use your legs, take the start, run away. My
[00:33.64] conscience says 'No; take heed,' honest Launcelot;
[00:38.12] take heed, honest Gobbo, or, as aforesaid, 'honest
[00:39.96] says the fiend, 'and run.' Well, my conscience,
[00:43.14] hanging about the neck of my heart, says very wisely
[00:43.31] Launcelot Gobbo; do not run; scorn running with thy
[00:45.99] heels.' Well, the most courageous fiend bids me
[00:46.97] to me 'My honest friend Launcelot, being an honest
[00:50.01] pack: 'Via!' says the fiend; 'away!' says the
[00:50.54] fiend; 'for the heavens, rouse up a brave mind,'
[00:50.61] man's son,' or rather an honest woman's son; for,
[00:54.05] indeed, my father did something smack, something
[00:57.56] grow to, he had a kind of taste; well, my conscience
[01:01.26] says 'Launcelot, budge not.' 'Budge,' says the
[01:04.31] fiend. 'Budge not,' says my conscience.
[01:07.02] 'Conscience,' say I, 'you counsel well;' ' Fiend,'
[01:10.06] say I, 'you counsel well:' to be ruled by my
[01:13.17] conscience, I should stay with the Jew my master,
[01:16.75] who, God bless the mark, is a kind of devil; and, to
[01:20.39] run away from the Jew, I should be ruled by the
[01:23.89] fiend, who, saving your reverence, is the devil
[01:27.27] himself. Certainly the Jew is the very devil
[01:30.58] incarnal; and, in my conscience, my conscience is
[01:34.08] but a kind of hard conscience, to offer to counsel
[01:37.79] me to stay with the Jew. The fiend gives the more
[01:41.43] friendly counsel: I will run, fiend; my heels are
[01:44.93] at your command; I will run.
[01:47.12] [Enter Old GOBBO, with a basket]
[01:47.91]GOBBO Master young man, you, I pray you, which is the way
[01:51.55] to master Jew's?
[01:53.01]LAUNCELOT [Aside] O heavens, this is my true-begotten father!
[01:56.58] who, being more than sand-blind, high-gravel blind,
[02:00.22] knows me not: I will try confusions with him.
[02:03.53]GOBBO Master young gentleman, I pray you, which is the way
[02:07.30] to master Jew's?
[02:08.75]LAUNCELOT Turn up on your right hand at the next turning, but,
[02:12.52] at the next turning of all, on your left; marry, at
[02:16.16] the very next turning, turn of no hand, but turn
[02:19.67] down indirectly to the Jew's house.
[02:22.38]GOBBO By God's sonties, 'twill be a hard way to hit. Can
[02:25.96] you tell me whether one Launcelot,
[02:28.60] that dwells with him, dwell with him or no?
[02:31.78]LAUNCELOT Talk you of young Master Launcelot?
[02:34.49] [Aside]
[02:35.29] Mark me now; now will I raise the waters. Talk you
[02:38.93] of young Master Launcelot?
[02:41.04]GOBBO No master, sir, but a poor man's son: his father,
[02:44.48] though I say it, is an honest exceeding poor man
[02:48.06] and, God be thanked, well to live.
[02:50.57]LAUNCELOT Well, let his father be what a' will, we talk of
[02:54.01] young Master Launcelot.
[02:55.93]GOBBO Your worship's friend and Launcelot, sir.
[02:58.97]LAUNCELOT But I pray you, ergo, old man, ergo, I beseech you,
[03:02.48] talk you of young Master Launcelot?
[03:05.19]GOBBO Of Launcelot, an't please your mastership.
[03:08.30]LAUNCELOT Ergo, Master Launcelot. Talk not of Master
[03:11.41] Launcelot, father; for the young gentleman,
[03:14.52] according to Fates and Destinies and such odd
[03:17.96] sayings, the Sisters Three and such branches of
[03:21.47] learning, is indeed deceased, or, as you would say
[03:25.04] in plain terms, gone to heaven.
[03:27.42]GOBBO Marry, God forbid! the boy was the very staff of my
[03:31.13] age, my very prop.
[03:32.65]LAUNCELOT Do I look like a cudgel or a hovel-post, a staff or
[03:36.42] a prop? Do you know me, father?
[03:38.74]GOBBO Alack the day, I know you not, young gentleman:
[03:42.11] but, I pray you, tell me, is my boy, God rest his
[03:45.55] soul, alive or dead?
[03:47.21]LAUNCELOT Do you not know me, father?
[03:49.33]GOBBO Alack, sir, I am sand-blind; I know you not.
[03:52.44]LAUNCELOT Nay, indeed, if you had your eyes, you might fail of
[03:56.14] the knowing me: it is a wise father that knows his
[03:59.85] own child. Well, old man, I will tell you news of
[04:03.35] your son: give me your blessing: truth will come
[04:06.86] to light; murder cannot be hid long; a man's son
[04:10.37] may, but at the length truth will out.
[04:13.21]GOBBO Pray you, sir, stand up: I am sure you are not
[04:16.52] Launcelot, my boy.
[04:18.04]LAUNCELOT Pray you, let's have no more fooling about it, but
[04:21.68] give me your blessing: I am Launcelot, your boy
[04:25.12] that was, your son that is, your child that shall
[04:28.69] be.
[04:29.29]GOBBO I cannot think you are my son.
[04:31.67]LAUNCELOT I know not what I shall think of that: but I am
[04:35.18] Launcelot, the Jew's man, and I am sure Margery your
[04:38.95] wife is my mother.
[04:40.54]GOBBO Her name is Margery, indeed: I'll be sworn, if thou
[04:44.18] be Launcelot, thou art mine own flesh and blood.
[04:47.68] Lord worshipped might he be! what a beard hast thou
[04:51.46] got! thou hast got more hair on thy chin than
[04:54.83] Dobbin my fill-horse has on his tail.
[04:57.67]LAUNCELOT It should seem, then, that Dobbin's tail grows
[05:01.05] backward: I am sure he had more hair of his tail
[05:04.62] than I have of my face when I last saw him.
[05:07.86]GOBBO Lord, how art thou changed! How dost thou and thy
[05:11.44] master agree? I have brought him a present. How
[05:14.88] 'gree you now?
[05:16.13]LAUNCELOT Well, well: but, for mine own part, as I have set
[05:19.58] up my rest to run away, so I will not rest till I
[05:23.21] have run some ground. My master's a very Jew: give
[05:26.85] him a present! give him a halter: I am famished in
[05:30.49] his service; you may tell every finger I have with
[05:34.20] my ribs. Father, I am glad you are come: give me
[05:37.64] your present to one Master Bassanio, who, indeed,
[05:41.15] gives rare new liveries: if I serve not him, I
[05:44.52] will run as far as God has any ground. O rare
[05:47.89] fortune! here comes the man: to him, father; for I
[05:51.40] am a Jew, if I serve the Jew any longer.
[05:54.38] [Enter BASSANIO, with LEONARDO and other followers]
[05:55.17]BASSANIO You may do so; but let it be so hasted that supper
[05:58.88] be ready at the farthest by five of the clock. See
[06:02.58] these letters delivered; put the liveries to making,
[06:06.35] and desire Gratiano to come anon to my lodging.
[06:09.86] [Exit a Servant]
[06:10.66]LAUNCELOT To him, father.
[06:11.98]GOBBO God bless your worship!
[06:13.90]BASSANIO Gramercy! wouldst thou aught with me?
[06:16.68]GOBBO Here's my son, sir, a poor boy,--
[06:18.99]LAUNCELOT Not a poor boy, sir, but the rich Jew's man; that
[06:22.50] would, sir, as my father shall specify--
[06:25.34]GOBBO He hath a great infection, sir, as one would say, to serve--
[06:29.45]LAUNCELOT Indeed, the short and the long is, I serve the Jew,
[06:33.09] and have a desire, as my father shall specify--
[06:36.46]GOBBO His master and he, saving your worship's reverence,
[06:40.17] are scarce cater-cousins--
[06:42.22]LAUNCELOT To be brief, the very truth is that the Jew, having
[06:45.92] done me wrong, doth cause me, as my father, being, I
[06:49.56] hope, an old man, shall frutify unto you--
[06:52.54]GOBBO I have here a dish of doves that I would bestow upon
[06:56.44] your worship, and my suit is--
[06:58.69]LAUNCELOT In very brief, the suit is impertinent to myself, as
[07:02.46] your worship shall know by this honest old man; and,
[07:06.23] though I say it, though old man, yet poor man, my father.
[07:10.20]BASSANIO One speak for both. What would you?
[07:12.85]LAUNCELOT Serve you, sir.
[07:14.17]GOBBO That is the very defect of the matter, sir.
[07:17.35]BASSANIO I know thee well; thou hast obtain'd thy suit:
[07:20.72] Shylock thy master spoke with me this day,
[07:23.90] And hath preferr'd thee, if it be preferment
[07:27.21] To leave a rich Jew's service, to become
[07:30.25] The follower of so poor a gentleman.
[07:33.03]LAUNCELOT The old proverb is very well parted between my
[07:36.54] master Shylock and you, sir: you have the grace of
[07:40.18] God, sir, and he hath enough.
[07:42.36]BASSANIO Thou speak'st it well. Go, father, with thy son.
[07:45.74] Take leave of thy old master and inquire
[07:48.85] My lodging out. Give him a livery
[07:51.43] More guarded than his fellows': see it done.
[07:54.60]LAUNCELOT Father, in. I cannot get a service, no; I have
[07:57.84] ne'er a tongue in my head. Well, if any man in
[08:01.22] Italy have a fairer table which doth offer to swear
[08:05.06] upon a book, I shall have good fortune. Go to,
[08:08.36] here's a simple line of life: here's a small trifle
[08:12.14] of wives: alas, fifteen wives is nothing! eleven
[08:15.58] widows and nine maids is a simple coming-in for one
[08:19.41] man: and then to 'scape drowning thrice, and to be
[08:22.99] in peril of my life with the edge of a feather-bed;
[08:26.76] here are simple scapes. Well, if Fortune be a
[08:30.07] woman, she's a good wench for this gear. Father,
[08:33.51] come; I'll take my leave of the Jew in the twinkling of an eye.
[08:38.01] [Exeunt Launcelot and Old Gobbo]
[08:38.80]BASSANIO I pray thee, good Leonardo, think on this:
[08:41.84] These things being bought and orderly bestow'd,
[08:45.35] Return in haste, for I do feast to-night
[08:48.39] My best-esteem'd acquaintance: hie thee, go.
[08:51.57]LEONARDO My best endeavours shall be done herein.
[08:54.61] [Enter GRATIANO]
[08:55.41]GRATIANO Where is your master?
[08:57.19]LEONARDO Yonder, sir, he walks.
[08:58.91] [Exit]
[08:59.71]GRATIANO Signior Bassanio!
[09:01.23]BASSANIO Gratiano!
[09:02.22]GRATIANO I have a suit to you.
[09:04.01]BASSANIO You have obtain'd it.
[09:05.80]GRATIANO You must not deny me: I must go with you to Belmont.
[09:09.57]BASSANIO Why then you must. But hear thee, Gratiano;
[09:12.68] Thou art too wild, too rude and bold of voice;
[09:16.05] Parts that become thee happily enough
[09:18.96] And in such eyes as ours appear not faults;
[09:22.21] But where thou art not known, why, there they show
[09:25.84] Something too liberal. Pray thee, take pain
[09:29.02] To allay with some cold drops of modesty
[09:32.13] Thy skipping spirit, lest through thy wild behavior
[09:35.90] I be misconstrued in the place I go to,
[09:38.88] And lose my hopes.
[09:40.47]GRATIANO Signior Bassanio, hear me:
[09:42.52] If I do not put on a sober habit,
[09:45.10] Talk with respect and swear but now and then,
[09:48.47] Wear prayer-books in my pocket, look demurely,
[09:51.85] Nay more, while grace is saying, hood mine eyes
[09:55.29] Thus with my hat, and sigh and say 'amen,'
[09:58.27] Use all the observance of civility,
[10:00.98] Like one well studied in a sad ostent
[10:03.89] To please his grandam, never trust me more.
[10:07.07]BASSANIO Well, we shall see your bearing.
[10:09.51]GRATIANO Nay, but I bar to-night: you shall not gauge me
[10:12.95] By what we do to-night.
[10:14.87]BASSANIO No, that were pity:
[10:16.46] I would entreat you rather to put on
[10:19.31] Your boldest suit of mirth, for we have friends
[10:22.81] That purpose merriment. But fare you well:
[10:25.92] I have some business.
[10:27.71]GRATIANO And I must to Lorenzo and the rest:
[10:30.42] But we will visit you at supper-time.
[10:33.27] [Exeunt]
[10:34.00] ./Plays/14-Merchant-of-Venice/14-Merchant-of-Venice-Act-2-Scene-2.mp3 ./Plays/14-Merchant-of-Venice/14-Merchant-of-Venice-Act-2-Scene-2.lrc
