[00:44.86] [Enter FLAVIUS, MARULLUS, and certain Commoners]
[01:09.58]FLAVIUS Hence! home, you idle creatures get you home:
[01:11.61] [Rome. A street.,]
[01:12.39] Is this a holiday? what! know you not,
[01:16.43] Upon a labouring day without the sign
[01:20.64] Of your profession? Speak, what trade art thou?
[01:24.81]First Commoner Why, sir, a carpenter.
[01:26.61]MARULLUS Where is thy leather apron and thy rule?
[01:27.95] Being mechanical, you ought not walk
[01:29.60] What dost thou with thy best apparel on?
[01:30.51] You, sir, what trade are you?
[01:34.59]Second Commoner Truly, sir, in respect of a fine workman, I am but,
[01:46.18] as you would say, a cobbler.
[01:46.70]MARULLUS But what trade art thou? answer me directly.
[01:47.33]Second Commoner A trade, sir, that, I hope, I may use with a safe
[01:47.92]MARULLUS What trade, thou knave? thou naughty knave, what trade?
[01:49.84] conscience; which is, indeed, sir, a mender of bad soles.
[01:51.56]Second Commoner Nay, I beseech you, sir, be not out with me: yet,
[01:54.70] if you be out, sir, I can mend you.
[02:00.13]Second Commoner Why, sir, cobble you.
[02:04.10]MARULLUS What meanest thou by that? mend me, thou saucy fellow!  [55]
[02:08.58]FLAVIUS Thou art a cobbler, art thou?
[02:08.96]Second Commoner Truly, sir, all that I live by is with the awl: I
[02:11.91] meddle with no tradesman's matters, nor women's
[02:13.96] to old shoes; when they are in great danger, I
[02:16.46] matters, but with awl. I am, indeed, sir, a surgeon
[02:20.05] recover them. As proper men as ever trod upon
[02:23.30] neat's leather have gone upon my handiwork.
[02:27.40]FLAVIUS But wherefore art not in thy shop today?
[02:29.44] Why dost thou lead these men about the streets?
[02:32.45] into more work. But, indeed, sir, we make holiday,
[02:35.59]Second Commoner Truly, sir, to wear out their shoes, to get myself
[02:40.71] to see Caesar and to rejoice in his triumph.
[02:45.71]MARULLUS Wherefore rejoice? What conquest brings he home?
[02:50.50] What tributaries follow him to Rome,
[02:55.62] To grace in captive bonds his chariot-wheels?
[03:00.29] You blocks, you stones, you worse than senseless things!
[03:05.34] O you hard hearts, you cruel men of Rome,
[03:10.59] Knew you not Pompey? Many a time and oft
[03:14.43] Have you climb'd up to walls and battlements,
[03:16.49] To towers and windows, yea, to chimney-tops,
[03:17.25] Your infants in your arms, and there have sat
[03:17.64] The livelong day, with patient expectation,
[03:19.75] To see great Pompey pass the streets of Rome:
[03:20.59] And when you saw his chariot but appear,
[03:22.50] Have you not made an universal shout,
[03:23.98] That Tiber trembled underneath her banks,
[03:26.15] To hear the replication of your sounds
[03:27.56] Made in her concave shores?
[03:29.17] And do you now put on your best attire?
[03:30.31] And do you now cull out a holiday?
[03:34.02] And do you now strew flowers in his way
[03:38.56] That comes in triumph over Pompey's blood? Be gone!
[03:43.80] Run to your houses, fall upon your knees,
[03:45.28] Pray to the gods to intermit the plague
[03:47.47] That needs must light on this ingratitude.
[03:50.33]FLAVIUS Go, go, good countrymen, and, for this fault,
[03:51.24] Assemble all the poor men of your sort;
[03:53.29] Draw them to Tiber banks, and weep your tears
[03:55.85] Into the channel, till the lowest stream
[03:57.89] Do kiss the most exalted shores of all.
[04:04.11] [Exeunt all the Commoners]
[04:06.48] See whether their basest metal be not moved;
[04:09.04] Go you down that way towards the Capitol;
[04:13.14] They vanish tongue-tied in their guiltiness.
[04:14.35] This way will I
[04:16.06] disrobe the images,
[04:17.61] If you do find them deck'd with ceremonies.
[04:19.08]MARULLUS May we do so?
[04:20.55] You know it is the feast of Lupercal.
[04:22.14]FLAVIUS It is no matter; let no images
[04:23.75] Be hung with Caesar's trophies. I'll about,
[04:26.31] And drive away the vulgar from the streets:
[04:28.67] So do you too, where you perceive them thick.
[04:32.84] These growing feathers pluck'd from Caesar's wing
[04:36.94] Will make him fly an ordinary pitch,
[04:39.63] Who else would soar above the view of men
[04:42.44] [Exeunt]
[04:43.12] And keep us all in servile fearfulness.
[04:43.35] ./Plays/18-Julius-Caesar/18-Julius-Caesar-Act-1-Scene-1.mp3 ./Plays/18-Julius-Caesar/18-Julius-Caesar-Act-1-Scene-1.lrc
