[00:00.48] [A street near the Capitol.,]
[00:01.44] [Enter ARTEMIDORUS, reading a paper]
[00:08.39]ARTEMIDORUS 'Caesar, beware of Brutus; take heed of Cassius;
[00:11.65] come not near Casca; have an eye to Cinna, trust not
[00:17.03] Trebonius: mark well Metellus Cimber: Decius Brutus
[00:20.04] loves thee not: thou hast wronged Caius Ligarius.
[00:24.19] There is but one mind in all these men, and it is
[00:28.16] bent against Caesar. If thou beest not immortal,
[00:31.87] look about you: security gives way to conspiracy.
[00:38.02] The mighty gods defend thee! Thy lover, 'ARTEMIDORUS.'
[00:43.26] Here will I stand till Caesar pass along,
[00:45.19] And as a suitor will I give him this.
[00:48.32] My heart laments that virtue cannot live
[00:50.57] Out of the teeth of emulation.
[00:54.35] If thou read this, O Caesar, thou mayst live;
[00:59.34] If not, the Fates with traitors do contrive.
[00:59.89] [Exit]
[01:00.00] ./Plays/18-Julius-Caesar/18-Julius-Caesar-Act-2-Scene-3.mp3 ./Plays/18-Julius-Caesar/18-Julius-Caesar-Act-2-Scene-3.lrc
