[00:00.40] [A public place.,]
[00:01.20] [Flourish. Enter CAESAR; ANTONY, for the course;
[00:08.20] + CALPURNIA, PORTIA, DECIUS BRUTUS, CICERO, BRUTUS,
[00:11.98] + CASSIUS, and CASCA; a great crowd following, among
[00:14.99] + them a Soothsayer]
[00:16.64]CAESAR Calpurnia!
[00:21.82]CASCA Peace, ho! Caesar speaks.
[00:23.43]CAESAR Calpurnia!
[00:24.71]CALPURNIA Here, my lord.
[00:27.14]CAESAR Stand you directly in Antonius' way,
[00:29.64] When he doth run his course. Antonius!
[00:31.31]ANTONY Caesar, my lord?
[00:32.72]CAESAR Forget not, in your speed, Antonius,
[00:35.59] To touch Calpurnia; for our elders say,
[00:37.51] The barren, touched in this holy chase,
[00:39.54] Shake off their sterile curse.
[00:40.71]ANTONY I shall remember:
[00:42.30] When Caesar says 'do this,' it is perform'd.
[00:47.30]CAESAR Set on; and leave no ceremony out.
[00:48.01] [Flourish]
[00:48.33]Soothsayer Caesar!
[00:49.29]CAESAR Ha! who calls?
[00:50.83]CASCA Bid every noise be still: peace yet again!
[00:53.76]CAESAR Who is it in the press that calls on me?
[00:55.89] I hear a tongue, shriller than all the music,
[00:59.20] Cry 'Caesar!' Speak; Caesar is turn'd to hear.
[01:01.51]Soothsayer Beware the ides of March.
[01:02.92]CAESAR What man is that?
[01:06.31]BRUTUS A soothsayer bids you beware the ides of March.
[01:07.84]CAESAR Set him before me; let me see his face.
[01:12.82]CASSIUS Fellow, come from the throng; look upon Caesar.
[01:15.52]CAESAR What say'st thou to me now? speak once again.
[01:19.05]Soothsayer Beware the ides of March.
[01:24.05]CAESAR He is a dreamer; let us leave him: pass.
[01:31.40] [Sennet. Exeunt all except BRUTUS and CASSIUS]
[01:32.62]CASSIUS Will you go see the order of the course?
[01:34.59]BRUTUS Not I.
[01:35.68]CASSIUS I pray you, do.
[01:39.83]BRUTUS I am not gamesome: I do lack some part
[01:42.40] Of that quick spirit that is in Antony.
[01:44.77] Let me not hinder, Cassius, your desires;
[01:47.02] I'll leave you.
[01:51.62]CASSIUS Brutus, I do observe you now of late:
[01:54.89] I have not from your eyes that gentleness
[01:56.67] And show of love as I was wont to have:
[02:00.25] You bear too stubborn and too strange a hand
[02:01.79] Over your friend that loves you.
[02:02.95]BRUTUS Cassius,
[02:04.75] Be not deceived: if I have veil'd my look,
[02:09.80] I turn the trouble of my countenance
[02:12.49] Merely upon myself. Vexed I am
[02:14.86] Of late with passions of some difference,
[02:16.76] Conceptions only proper to myself,
[02:19.38] Which give some soil perhaps to my behaviors;
[02:23.11] But let not therefore my good friends be grieved--
[02:25.49] Among which number, Cassius, be you one--
[02:28.17] Nor construe any further my neglect,
[02:30.22] Than that poor Brutus, with himself at war,
[02:33.53] Forgets the shows of love to other men.
[02:35.85]CASSIUS Then, Brutus, I have much mistook your passion;
[02:40.20] By means whereof this breast of mine hath buried
[02:42.76] Thoughts of great value, worthy cogitations.
[02:47.74] Tell me, good Brutus, can you see your face?
[02:52.54]BRUTUS No, Cassius; for the eye sees not itself,
[02:55.49] But by reflection, by some other things.
[02:57.29]CASSIUS 'Tis just:
[02:59.79] And it is very much lamented, Brutus,
[03:02.41] That you have no such mirrors as will turn
[03:03.76] Your hidden worthiness into your eye,
[03:07.96] That you might see your shadow. I have heard,
[03:09.90] Where many of the best respect in Rome,
[03:13.54] Except immortal Caesar, speaking of Brutus
[03:15.52] And groaning underneath this age's yoke,
[03:18.79] Have wish'd that noble Brutus had his eyes.
[03:22.63]BRUTUS Into what dangers would you lead me, Cassius,
[03:25.06] That you would have me seek into myself
[03:26.53] For that which is not in me?
[03:28.20]CASSIUS Therefore, good Brutus, be prepared to hear:
[03:31.33] And since you know you cannot see yourself
[03:34.73] So well as by reflection, I, your glass,
[03:37.17] Will modestly discover to yourself
[03:39.27] That of yourself which you yet know not of.
[03:43.56] And be not jealous on me, gentle Brutus:
[03:45.61] Were I a common laugher, or did use
[03:47.02] To stale with ordinary oaths my love
[03:50.21] To every new protester; if you know
[03:52.65] That I do fawn on men and hug them hard
[03:55.45] And after scandal them, or if you know
[03:57.06] That I profess myself in banqueting
[04:00.39] To all the rout, then hold me dangerous.
[04:02.95] [Flourish, and shout]
[04:05.63]BRUTUS What means this shouting? I do fear, the people
[04:07.50] Choose Caesar for their king.
[04:09.54]CASSIUS Ay, do you fear it?
[04:12.02] Then must I think you would not have it so.
[04:15.81]BRUTUS I would not, Cassius; yet I love him well.
[04:19.28] But wherefore do you hold me here so long?
[04:21.90] What is it that you would impart to me?
[04:24.52] If it be aught toward the general good,
[04:27.84] Set honour in one eye and death i' the other,
[04:29.88] And I will look on both indifferently,
[04:31.62] For let the gods so speed me as I love
[04:34.18] The name of honour more than I fear death.
[04:35.72]CASSIUS I know that virtue to be in you, Brutus,
[04:38.90] As well as I do know your outward favour.
[04:43.46] Well, honour is the subject of my story.
[04:47.04] I cannot tell what you and other men
[04:50.19] Think of this life; but, for my single self,
[04:53.45] I had as lief not be as live to be
[04:56.01] In awe of such a thing as I myself.
[04:58.82] I was born free as Caesar; so were you:
[05:04.32] We both have fed as well, and we can both
[05:05.67] Endure the winter's cold as well as he:
[05:09.07] For once, upon a raw and gusty day,
[05:11.43] The troubled Tiber chafing with her shores,
[05:16.03] Caesar said to me 'Darest thou, Cassius, now
[05:17.90] Leap in with me into this angry flood,
[05:21.21] And swim to yonder point?' Upon the word,
[05:23.41] Accoutred as I was, I plunged in
[05:25.97] And bade him follow; so indeed he did.
[05:29.98] The torrent roar'd, and we did buffet it
[05:32.30] With lusty sinews, throwing it aside
[05:34.34] And stemming it with hearts of controversy;
[05:37.10] But ere we could arrive the point proposed,
[05:40.87] Caesar cried 'Help me, Cassius, or I sink!'
[05:45.86] I, as Aeneas, our great ancestor,
[05:48.42] Did from the flames of Troy upon his shoulder
[05:51.11] The old Anchises bear, so from the waves of Tiber
[05:55.15] Did I the tired Caesar. And this man
[05:58.66] Is now become a god, and Cassius is
[06:01.16] A wretched creature and must bend his body,
[06:04.24] If Caesar carelessly but nod on him.
[06:06.34] He had a fever when he was in Spain,
[06:08.83] And when the fit was on him, I did mark
[06:12.05] How he did shake: 'tis true, this god did shake;
[06:15.30] His coward lips did from their colour fly,
[06:18.19] And that same eye whose bend doth awe the world
[06:21.00] Did lose his lustre: I did hear him groan:
[06:24.58] Ay, and that tongue of his that bade the Romans
[06:26.95] Mark him and write his speeches in their books,
[06:30.21] Alas, it cried 'Give me some drink, Titinius,'
[06:35.02] As a sick girl. Ye gods, it doth amaze me
[06:36.93] A man of such a feeble temper should
[06:38.47] So get the start of the majestic world
[06:39.75] And bear the palm alone.
[06:41.36] [Shout. Flourish]
[06:43.07]BRUTUS Another general shout!
[06:44.42] I do believe that these applauses are
[06:46.60] For some new honours that are heap'd on Caesar.
[06:49.66]CASSIUS Why, man, he doth bestride the narrow world
[06:50.95] Like a Colossus, and we petty men
[06:53.31] Walk under his huge legs and peep about
[06:55.04] To find ourselves dishonourable graves.
[06:58.62] Men at some time are masters of their fates:
[07:01.18] The fault, dear Brutus, is not in our stars,
[07:05.67] But in ourselves, that we are underlings.
[07:13.79] Brutus and Caesar: what should be in that 'Caesar'?
[07:17.07] Why should that name be sounded more than yours?
[07:19.50] Write them together, yours is as fair a name;
[07:22.38] Sound them, it doth become the mouth as well;
[07:25.83] Weigh them, it is as heavy; conjure with 'em,
[07:27.74] Brutus will start a spirit as soon as Caesar.
[07:31.01] Now, in the names of all the gods at once,
[07:33.64] Upon what meat doth this our Caesar feed,
[07:38.96] That he is grown so great? Age, thou art shamed!
[07:42.73] Rome, thou hast lost the breed of noble bloods!
[07:46.12] When went there by an age, since the great flood,
[07:48.48] But it was famed with more than with one man?
[07:51.89] When could they say till now, that talk'd of Rome,
[07:53.80] That her wide walls encompass'd but one man?
[07:56.42] Now is it Rome indeed and room enough,
[07:59.75] When there is in it but one only man.
[08:03.84] O, you and I have heard our fathers say,
[08:06.08] There was a Brutus once that would have brook'd
[08:08.01] The eternal devil to keep his state in Rome
[08:09.48] As easily as a king.
[08:13.12]BRUTUS That you do love me, I am nothing jealous;
[08:17.23] What you would work me to, I have some aim:
[08:21.13] How I have thought of this and of these times,
[08:24.00] I shall recount hereafter; for this present,
[08:26.50] I would not, so with love I might entreat you,
[08:29.90] Be any further moved. What you have said
[08:33.67] I will consider; what you have to say
[08:35.77] I will with patience hear, and find a time
[08:38.92] Both meet to hear and answer such high things.
[08:44.54] Till then, my noble friend, chew upon this:
[08:49.98] Brutus had rather be a villager
[08:51.85] Than to repute himself a son of Rome
[08:54.84] Under these hard conditions as this time
[08:56.97] Is like to lay upon us.
[08:59.47]CASSIUS I am glad that my weak words
[09:02.46] Have struck but thus much show of fire from Brutus.
[09:07.02]BRUTUS The games are done and Caesar is returning.
[09:09.31]CASSIUS As they pass by, pluck Casca by the sleeve;
[09:13.22] And he will, after his sour fashion, tell you
[09:15.38] What hath proceeded worthy note to-day.
[09:17.26] [Re-enter CAESAR and his Train]
[09:18.40]BRUTUS I will do so. But, look you, Cassius,
[09:22.57] The angry spot doth glow on Caesar's brow,
[09:24.61] And all the rest look like a chidden train:
[09:28.18] Calpurnia's cheek is pale; and Cicero
[09:30.94] Looks with such ferret and such fiery eyes
[09:32.49] As we have seen him in the Capitol,
[09:34.91] Being cross'd in conference by some senators.
[09:36.52]CASSIUS Casca will tell us what the matter is.
[09:38.82]CAESAR Antonius!
[09:39.77]ANTONY Caesar?
[09:42.03]CAESAR Let me have men about me that are fat;
[09:45.98] Sleek-headed men and such as sleep o' nights:
[09:49.77] Yond Cassius has a lean and hungry look;
[09:52.96] He thinks too much: such men are dangerous.
[09:55.53]ANTONY Fear him not, Caesar; he's not dangerous;
[09:58.28] He is a noble Roman and well given.
[10:01.40]CAESAR Would he were fatter! But I fear him not:
[10:04.94] Yet if my name were liable to fear,
[10:06.98] I do not know the man I should avoid
[10:11.28] So soon as that spare Cassius. He reads much;
[10:14.46] He is a great observer and he looks
[10:18.43] Quite through the deeds of men: he loves no plays,
[10:22.34] As thou dost, Antony; he hears no music;
[10:26.31] Seldom he smiles, and smiles in such a sort
[10:29.82] As if he mock'd himself and scorn'd his spirit
[10:32.84] That could be moved to smile at any thing.
[10:35.14] Such men as he be never at heart's ease
[10:37.70] Whiles they behold a greater than themselves,
[10:40.26] And therefore are they very dangerous.
[10:43.91] I rather tell thee what is to be fear'd
[10:47.55] Than what I fear; for always I am Caesar.
[10:52.54] Come on my right hand, for this ear is deaf,
[10:56.63] And tell me truly what thou think'st of him.
[11:00.67] [Sennet. Exeunt CAESAR and all his Train, but CASCA]
[11:07.47]CASCA You pull'd me by the cloak; would you speak with me?
[11:11.11]BRUTUS Ay, Casca; tell us what hath chanced to-day,
[11:12.26] That Caesar looks so sad.
[11:14.69]CASCA Why, you were with him, were you not?
[11:17.70]BRUTUS I should not then ask Casca what had chanced.
[11:21.74]CASCA Why, there was a crown offered him: and being
[11:23.98] offered him, he put it by with the back of his hand,
[11:26.60] thus; and then the people fell a-shouting.
[11:28.64]BRUTUS What was the second noise for?
[11:29.92]CASCA Why, for that too.
[11:32.11]CASSIUS They shouted thrice: what was the last cry for?
[11:33.44]CASCA Why, for that too.
[11:35.43]BRUTUS Was the crown offered him thrice?
[11:38.32]CASCA Ay, marry, was't, and he put it by thrice, every
[11:40.88] time gentler than other, and at every putting-by
[11:42.53] mine honest neighbours shouted.
[11:43.74]CASSIUS Who offered him the crown?
[11:44.72]CASCA Why, Antony.
[11:46.42]BRUTUS Tell us the manner of it, gentle Casca.
[11:49.58]CASCA I can as well be hanged as tell the manner of it:
[11:53.35] it was mere foolery; I did not mark it. I saw Mark
[11:56.93] Antony offer him a crown;--yet 'twas not a crown
[11:59.69] neither, 'twas one of these coronets;--and, as I told
[12:02.83] you, he put it by once: but, for all that, to my
[12:05.39] thinking, he would fain have had it. Then he
[12:07.63] offered it to him again; then he put it by again:
[12:09.66] but, to my thinking, he was very loath to lay his
[12:13.07] fingers off it. And then he offered it the third
[12:17.41] time; he put it the third time by: and still as he
[12:19.84] refused it, the rabblement hooted and clapped their
[12:22.34] chapped hands and threw up their sweaty night-caps
[12:25.99] and uttered such a deal of stinking breath because
[12:27.84] Caesar refused the crown that it had almost choked
[12:30.47] Caesar; for he swounded and fell down at it: and
[12:32.64] for mine own part, I durst not laugh, for fear of
[12:34.38] opening my lips and receiving the bad air.
[12:36.81]CASSIUS But, soft, I pray you: what, did Caesar swound?
[12:39.23]CASCA He fell down in the market-place, and foamed at
[12:41.35] mouth, and was speechless.
[12:43.60]BRUTUS 'Tis very like: he hath the failing sickness.
[12:46.09]CASSIUS No, Caesar hath it not; but you and I,
[12:49.03] And honest Casca, we have the falling sickness.
[12:52.92]CASCA I know not what you mean by that; but, I am sure,
[12:56.59] Caesar fell down. If the tag-rag people did not
[12:59.21] clap him and hiss him, according as he pleased and
[13:01.13] displeased them, as they use to do the players in
[13:03.75] the theatre, I am no true man.
[13:05.16]BRUTUS What said he when he came unto himself?
[13:08.34]CASCA Marry, before he fell down, when he perceived the
[13:10.72] common herd was glad he refused the crown, he
[13:12.97] plucked me ope his doublet and offered them his
[13:14.95] throat to cut. An I had been a man of any
[13:17.44] occupation, if I would not have taken him at a word,
[13:20.13] I would I might go to hell among the rogues. And so
[13:22.89] he fell. When he came to himself again, he said,
[13:25.77] If he had done or said any thing amiss, he desired
[13:30.63] their worships to think it was his infirmity. Three
[13:34.21] or four wenches, where I stood, cried 'Alas, good
[13:35.88] soul!' and forgave him with all their hearts: but
[13:37.99] there's no heed to be taken of them; if Caesar had
[13:39.66] stabbed their mothers, they would have done no less.
[13:42.91]BRUTUS And after that, he came, thus sad, away?
[13:44.78]CASCA Ay.
[13:47.73]CASSIUS Did Cicero say any thing?
[13:48.42]CASCA Ay, he spoke Greek.
[13:49.44]CASSIUS To what effect?
[13:51.05]CASCA Nay, an I tell you that, Ill ne'er look you i' the
[13:52.46] face again: but those that understood him smiled at
[13:55.77] one another and shook their heads; but, for mine own
[13:57.51] part, it was Greek to me. I could tell you more
[14:03.02] news too: Marullus and Flavius, for pulling scarfs
[14:08.33] off Caesar's images, are put to silence. Fare you
[14:10.51] well. There was more foolery yet, if I could
[14:12.28] remember it.
[14:13.76]CASSIUS Will you sup with me to-night, Casca?
[14:15.24]CASCA No, I am promised forth.
[14:17.28]CASSIUS Will you dine with me to-morrow?
[14:20.68]CASCA Ay, if I be alive and your mind hold and your dinner
[14:21.96] worth the eating.
[14:23.63]CASSIUS Good: I will expect you.
[14:26.95]CASCA Do so. Farewell, both.
[14:28.69] [Exit]
[14:31.67]BRUTUS What a blunt fellow is this grown to be!
[14:34.05] He was quick mettle when he went to school.
[14:35.46]CASSIUS So is he now in execution
[14:37.25] Of any bold or noble enterprise,
[14:38.60] However he puts on this tardy form.
[14:43.20] This rudeness is a sauce to his good wit,
[14:46.73] Which gives men stomach to digest his words
[14:47.30] With better appetite.
[14:51.34]BRUTUS And so it is. For this time I will leave you:
[14:56.65] To-morrow, if you please to speak with me,
[14:59.28] I will come home to you; or, if you will,
[15:00.86] Come home to me, and I will wait for you.
[15:05.09]CASSIUS I will do so: till then, think of the world.
[15:07.39] [Exit BRUTUS]
[15:19.76] Well, Brutus, thou art noble; yet, I see,
[15:21.40] Thy honourable metal may be wrought
[15:22.06] From that it is disposed: therefore it is meet
[15:24.36] That noble minds keep ever with their likes;
[15:30.13] For who so firm that cannot be seduced?
[15:33.64] Caesar doth bear me hard; but he loves Brutus:
[15:36.96] If I were Brutus now and he were Cassius,
[15:41.32] He should not humour me. I will this night,
[15:44.70] In several hands, in at his windows throw,
[15:46.57] As if they came from several citizens,
[15:50.79] Writings all tending to the great opinion
[15:53.47] That Rome holds of his name; wherein obscurely
[15:55.91] Caesar's ambition shall be glanced at:
[15:59.80] And after this let Caesar seat him sure;
[16:04.68] For we will shake him, or worse days endure.
[16:14.27] [Exit]
[16:38.00] ./Plays/18-Julius-Caesar/18-Julius-Caesar-Act-1-Scene-2.mp3 ./Plays/18-Julius-Caesar/18-Julius-Caesar-Act-1-Scene-2.lrc
