[00:00.43] [Another part of the same street, before the house of BRUTUS.,]
[00:01.30] [Enter PORTIA and LUCIUS]
[00:14.27]PORTIA I prithee, boy, run to the senate-house;
[00:16.45] Stay not to answer me, but get thee gone:
[00:18.89] Why dost thou stay?
[00:20.87]LUCIUS To know my errand, madam.
[00:22.41]PORTIA I would have had thee there, and here again,
[00:23.95] Ere I can tell thee what thou shouldst do there.
[00:28.55] O constancy, be strong upon my side,
[00:31.81] Set a huge mountain 'tween my heart and tongue!
[00:36.10] I have a man's mind, but a woman's might.
[00:38.99] How hard it is for women to keep counsel!
[00:41.55] Art thou here yet?
[00:43.72]LUCIUS Madam, what should I do?
[00:45.26] Run to the Capitol, and nothing else?
[00:47.43] And so return to you, and nothing else?
[00:50.44]PORTIA Yes, bring me word, boy, if thy lord look well,
[00:54.02] For he went sickly forth: and take good note
[00:56.58] What Caesar doth, what suitors press to him.
[00:59.47] Hark, boy! what noise is that?
[01:01.83]LUCIUS I hear none, madam.
[01:03.24]PORTIA Prithee, listen well;
[01:05.54] I heard a bustling rumour, like a fray,
[01:08.42] And the wind brings it from the Capitol.
[01:10.66]LUCIUS Sooth, madam, I hear nothing.
[01:11.42] [Enter the Soothsayer]
[01:13.48]PORTIA Come hither, fellow: which way hast thou been?
[01:15.15]Soothsayer At mine own house, good lady.
[01:16.10]PORTIA What is't o'clock?
[01:17.26]Soothsayer About the ninth hour, lady.
[01:18.74]PORTIA Is Caesar yet gone to the Capitol?
[01:21.36]Soothsayer Madam, not yet: I go to take my stand,
[01:23.13] To see him pass on to the Capitol.
[01:25.63]PORTIA Thou hast some suit to Caesar, hast thou not?
[01:28.51]Soothsayer That I have, lady: if it will please Caesar
[01:30.38] To be so good to Caesar as to hear me,
[01:33.07] I shall beseech him to befriend himself.
[01:36.19]PORTIA Why, know'st thou any harm's intended towards him?
[01:39.78]Soothsayer None that I know will be, much that I fear may chance.
[01:42.72] Good morrow to you. Here the street is narrow:
[01:45.09] The throng that follows Caesar at the heels,
[01:48.67] Of senators, of praetors, common suitors,
[01:50.34] Will crowd a feeble man almost to death:
[01:52.58] I'll get me to a place more void, and there
[01:54.70] Speak to great Caesar as he comes along.
[01:55.46] [Exit]
[02:04.23] The heavens speed thee in thine enterprise!
[02:08.85] Sure, the boy heard me: Brutus hath a suit
[02:12.66]PORTIA I must go in. Ay me, how weak a thing
[02:13.06] That Caesar will not grant. O, I grow faint.
[02:15.70] The heart of woman is! O Brutus,
[02:16.77] Run, Lucius, and commend me to my lord;
[02:20.74] Say I am merry: come to me again,
[02:23.95] And bring me word what he doth say to thee.
[02:32.45] [Exeunt severally]
[02:39.00] ./Plays/18-Julius-Caesar/18-Julius-Caesar-Act-2-Scene-4.mp3 ./Plays/18-Julius-Caesar/18-Julius-Caesar-Act-2-Scene-4.lrc
