[00:00.35] [The same. A street.,]
[00:08.27] [Thunder and lightning. Enter from opposite sides,
[00:09.29] + CASCA, with his sword drawn, and CICERO]
[00:12.30]CICERO Good even, Casca: brought you Caesar home?
[00:13.06] Why are you breathless? and why stare you so?
[00:14.41]CASCA Are not you moved, when all the sway of earth
[00:17.16] Shakes like a thing unfirm? O Cicero,
[00:19.66] I have seen tempests, when the scolding winds
[00:21.83] Have rived the knotty oaks, and I have seen
[00:23.50] The ambitious ocean swell and rage and foam,
[00:26.81] To be exalted with the threatening clouds:
[00:29.25] But never till to-night, never till now,
[00:32.19] Did I go through a tempest dropping fire.
[00:34.89] Either there is a civil strife in heaven,
[00:36.93] Or else the world, too saucy with the gods,
[00:38.92] Incenses them to send destruction.
[00:41.74]CICERO Why, saw you any thing more wonderful?
[00:49.61]CASCA A common slave--you know him well by sight--
[00:50.44] Held up his left hand, which did flame and burn
[00:50.94] Like twenty torches join'd, and yet his hand,
[00:54.67] Not sensible of fire, remain'd unscorch'd.
[00:57.23] Besides--I ha' not since put up my sword--
[00:59.01] Against the Capitol I met a lion,
[01:02.16] Who glared upon me, and went surly by,
[01:05.15] Without annoying me: and there were drawn
[01:07.47] Upon a heap a hundred ghastly women,
[01:09.58] Transformed with their fear; who swore they saw
[01:12.27] Men all in fire walk up and down the streets.
[01:17.65] And yesterday the bird of night did sit
[01:20.33] Even at noon-day upon the market-place,
[01:23.20] Hooting and shrieking. When these prodigies
[01:25.76] Do so conjointly meet, let not men say
[01:28.91] 'These are their reasons; they are natural;'
[01:31.96] For, I believe, they are portentous things
[01:34.28] Unto the climate that they point upon.
[01:36.96]CICERO Indeed, it is a strange-disposed time:
[01:40.93] But men may construe things after their fashion,
[01:43.61] Clean from the purpose of the things themselves.
[01:47.98] Come Caesar to the Capitol to-morrow?
[01:50.60]CASCA He doth; for he did bid Antonius
[01:52.57] Send word to you he would be there to-morrow.
[01:55.85]CICERO Good night then, Casca: this disturbed sky
[01:57.20] Is not to walk in.
[01:58.48]CASCA Farewell, Cicero.
[01:59.37] [Exit CICERO]
[02:03.73] [Enter CASSIUS]
[02:04.49]CASSIUS Who's there?
[02:05.38]CASCA A Roman.
[02:06.79]CASSIUS Casca, by your voice.
[02:08.39]CASCA Your ear is good. Cassius, what night is this!
[02:12.43]CASSIUS A very pleasing night to honest men.
[02:14.09]CASCA Who ever knew the heavens menace so?
[02:16.77]CASSIUS Those that have known the earth so full of faults.
[02:19.84] For my part, I have walk'd about the streets,
[02:21.59] Submitting me unto the perilous night,
[02:23.68] And, thus unbraced, Casca, as you see,
[02:25.78] Have bared my bosom to the thunder-stone;
[02:28.04] And when the cross blue lightning seem'd to open
[02:29.83] The breast of heaven, I did present myself
[02:31.82] Even in the aim and very flash of it.
[02:35.21]CASCA But wherefore did you so much tempt the heavens?
[02:37.70] It is the part of men to fear and tremble,
[02:40.06] When the most mighty gods by tokens send
[02:41.61] Such dreadful heralds to astonish us.
[02:44.49]CASSIUS You are dull, Casca, and those sparks of life
[02:45.90] That should be in a Roman you do want,
[02:49.81] Or else you use not. You look pale and gaze
[02:52.11] And put on fear and cast yourself in wonder,
[02:54.80] To see the strange impatience of the heavens:
[02:57.91] But if you would consider the true cause
[03:01.38] Why all these fires, why all these gliding ghosts,
[03:04.26] Why birds and beasts from quality and kind,
[03:06.32] Why old men fool and children calculate,
[03:09.18] Why all these things change from their ordinance
[03:11.44] Their natures and preformed faculties
[03:15.53] To monstrous quality,--why, you shall find
[03:17.45] That heaven hath infused them with these spirits,
[03:19.24] To make them instruments of fear and warning
[03:20.83] Unto some monstrous state.
[03:23.52] Now could I, Casca, name to thee a man
[03:25.12] Most like this dreadful night,
[03:27.22] That thunders, lightens, opens graves, and roars
[03:28.96] As doth the lion in the Capitol,
[03:31.79] A man no mightier than thyself or me
[03:34.60] In personal action, yet prodigious grown
[03:36.45] And fearful, as these strange eruptions are.
[03:39.78]CASCA 'Tis Caesar that you mean; is it not, Cassius?
[03:44.72]CASSIUS Let it be who it is: for Romans now
[03:47.34] Have thews and limbs like to their ancestors;
[03:49.84] But, woe the while! our fathers' minds are dead,
[03:52.64] And we are govern'd with our mothers' spirits;
[03:54.57] Our yoke and sufferance show us womanish.
[03:57.32]CASCA Indeed, they say the senators tomorrow
[03:59.05] Mean to establish Caesar as a king;
[04:01.36] And he shall wear his crown by sea and land,
[04:03.00] In every place, save here in Italy.
[04:05.44]CASSIUS I know where I will wear this dagger then;
[04:08.90] Cassius from bondage will deliver Cassius:
[04:11.60] Therein, ye gods, you make the weak most strong;
[04:13.83] Therein, ye gods, you tyrants do defeat:
[04:16.45] Nor stony tower, nor walls of beaten brass,
[04:19.08] Nor airless dungeon, nor strong links of iron,
[04:21.25] Can be retentive to the strength of spirit;
[04:24.40] But life, being weary of these worldly bars,
[04:26.04] Never lacks power to dismiss itself.
[04:28.66] If I know this, know all the world besides,
[04:30.34] That part of tyranny that I do bear
[04:31.88] I can shake off at pleasure.
[04:32.45] [Thunder still]
[04:33.92]CASCA So can I:
[04:35.20] So every bondman in his own hand bears
[04:37.39] The power to cancel his captivity.
[04:39.69]CASSIUS And why should Caesar be a tyrant then?
[04:41.80] Poor man! I know he would not be a wolf,
[04:44.16] But that he sees the Romans are but sheep:
[04:46.46] He were no lion, were not Romans hinds.
[04:49.08] Those that with haste will make a mighty fire
[04:50.75] Begin it with weak straws: what trash is Rome,
[04:56.20] What rubbish and what offal, when it serves
[04:57.55] For the base matter to illuminate
[05:01.12] So vile a thing as Caesar! But, O grief,
[05:06.05] Where hast thou led me? I perhaps speak this
[05:09.44] Before a willing bondman; then I know
[05:11.76] My answer must be made. But I am arm'd,
[05:13.29] And dangers are to me indifferent.
[05:15.91]CASCA You speak to Casca, and to such a man
[05:17.76] That is no fleering tell-tale. Hold, my hand:
[05:22.95] Be factious for redress of all these griefs,
[05:25.12] And I will set this foot of mine as far
[05:26.73] As who goes farthest.
[05:28.65]CASSIUS There's a bargain made.
[05:32.18] Now know you, Casca, I have moved already
[05:34.21] Some certain of the noblest-minded Romans
[05:35.82] To undergo with me an enterprise
[05:37.36] Of honourable-dangerous consequence;
[05:39.92] And I do know, by this, they stay for me
[05:42.02] In Pompey's porch: for now, this fearful night,
[05:44.13] There is no stir or walking in the streets;
[05:46.19] And the complexion of the element
[05:47.60] In favour's like the work we have in hand,
[05:49.96] Most bloody, fiery, and most terrible.
[05:52.78]CASCA Stand close awhile, for here comes one in haste.
[05:54.37]CASSIUS 'Tis Cinna; I do know him by his gait;
[05:55.70] He is a friend.
[05:56.49] [Enter CINNA]
[05:57.84] Cinna, where haste you so?
[06:00.52]CINNA To find out you. Who's that? Metellus Cimber?
[06:03.14]CASSIUS No, it is Casca; one incorporate
[06:05.64] To our attempts. Am I not stay'd for, Cinna?
[06:08.38]CINNA I am glad on 't. What a fearful night is this!
[06:10.94] There's two or three of us have seen strange sights.
[06:13.82]CASSIUS Am I not stay'd for? tell me.
[06:15.37]CINNA Yes, you are.
[06:16.71] O Cassius, if you could
[06:17.86] But win the noble Brutus to our party--
[06:19.20]CASSIUS Be you content: good Cinna, take this paper,
[06:23.05] And look you lay it in the praetor's chair,
[06:24.59] Where Brutus may but find it; and throw this
[06:27.02] In at his window; set this up with wax
[06:30.53] Upon old Brutus' statue: all this done,
[06:34.76] Repair to Pompey's porch, where you shall find us.
[06:37.00] Is Decius Brutus and Trebonius there?
[06:37.52]CINNA All but Metellus Cimber; and he's gone
[06:39.75] To seek you at your house. Well, I will hie,
[06:41.10] And so bestow these papers as you bade me.
[06:42.89]CASSIUS That done, repair to Pompey's theatre.
[06:44.16] [Exit CINNA]
[06:47.43] Come, Casca, you and I will yet ere day
[06:50.45] See Brutus at his house: three parts of him
[06:52.55] Is ours already, and the man entire
[06:55.24] Upon the next encounter yields him ours.
[06:58.56]CASCA O, he sits high in all the people's hearts:
[06:59.78] And that which would appear offence in us,
[07:02.46] His countenance, like richest alchemy,
[07:04.27] Will change to virtue and to worthiness.
[07:06.17]CASSIUS Him and his worth and our great need of him
[07:07.78] You have right well conceited. Let us go,
[07:10.60] For it is after midnight; and ere day
[07:13.10] We will awake him and be sure of him.
[07:29.93] [Exeunt]
[07:40.00] ./Plays/18-Julius-Caesar/18-Julius-Caesar-Act-1-Scene-3.mp3 ./Plays/18-Julius-Caesar/18-Julius-Caesar-Act-1-Scene-3.lrc
