[00:00.36] [A house in Rome.,]
[00:01.10] [ANTONY, OCTAVIUS, and LEPIDUS, seated at a table]
[00:06.21]ANTONY These many, then, shall die; their names are prick'd.
[00:10.44]OCTAVIUS Your brother too must die; consent you, Lepidus?
[00:13.77]LEPIDUS I do consent--
[00:13.95]OCTAVIUS Prick him down, Antony.
[00:17.23]LEPIDUS Upon condition Publius shall not live,
[00:19.33] Who is your sister's son, Mark Antony.
[00:25.53]ANTONY He shall not live; look, with a spot I damn him.
[00:29.57] But, Lepidus, go you to Caesar's house;
[00:32.65] Fetch the will hither, and we shall determine
[00:34.13] How to cut off some charge in legacies.
[00:35.84]LEPIDUS What, shall I find you here?
[00:37.51]OCTAVIUS Or here, or at the Capitol.
[00:43.20] [Exit LEPIDUS]
[00:45.39]ANTONY This is a slight unmeritable man,
[00:47.62] Meet to be sent on errands: is it fit,
[00:50.76] The three-fold world divided, he should stand
[00:52.23] One of the three to share it?
[00:53.44]OCTAVIUS So you thought him;
[00:54.61] And took his voice who should be prick'd to die,
[00:56.52] In our black sentence and proscription.
[00:59.01]ANTONY Octavius, I have seen more days than you:
[01:02.15] And though we lay these honours on this man,
[01:04.98] To ease ourselves of divers slanderous loads,
[01:06.88] He shall but bear them as the ass bears gold,
[01:08.80] To groan and sweat under the business,
[01:11.36] Either led or driven, as we point the way;
[01:13.42] And having brought our treasure where we will,
[01:15.52] Then take we down his load, and turn him off,
[01:17.19] Like to the empty ass, to shake his ears,
[01:19.83] And graze in commons.
[01:20.90]OCTAVIUS You may do your will;
[01:23.39] But he's a tried and valiant soldier.
[01:26.22]ANTONY So is my horse, Octavius; and for that
[01:28.13] I do appoint him store of provender:
[01:30.32] It is a creature that I teach to fight,
[01:32.42] To wind, to stop, to run directly on,
[01:34.85] His corporal motion govern'd by my spirit.
[01:36.84] And, in some taste, is Lepidus but so;
[01:40.56] He must be taught and train'd and bid go forth;
[01:43.19] A barren-spirited fellow; one that feeds
[01:45.61] On abjects, orts and imitations,
[01:47.91] Which, out of use and staled by other men,
[01:49.76] Begin his fashion: do not talk of him,
[01:55.33] But as a property. And now, Octavius,
[01:58.79] Listen great things:--Brutus and Cassius
[02:01.73] Are levying powers: we must straight make head:
[02:04.09] Therefore let our alliance be combined,
[02:06.53] Our best friends made, our means stretch'd
[02:09.15] And let us presently go sit in council,
[02:11.21] How covert matters may be best disclosed,
[02:13.38] And open perils surest answered.
[02:15.48]OCTAVIUS Let us do so: for we are at the stake,
[02:17.35] And bay'd about with many enemies;
[02:21.26] And some that smile have in their hearts, I fear,
[02:24.21] Millions of mischiefs.
[02:24.71] [Exeunt]
[02:27.00] ./Plays/18-Julius-Caesar/18-Julius-Caesar-Act-4-Scene-1.mp3 ./Plays/18-Julius-Caesar/18-Julius-Caesar-Act-4-Scene-1.lrc
