[00:00.47] [Another part of the field.,]
[00:09.98] [Alarum. Enter fighting, Soldiers of both armies;
[00:10.83] + then BRUTUS, CATO, LUCILIUS, and others]
[00:13.00]BRUTUS Yet, countrymen, O, yet hold up your heads!
[00:15.30]CATO What bastard doth not? Who will go with me?
[00:19.33] I will proclaim my name about the field:
[00:22.72] I am the son of Marcus Cato, ho!
[00:26.12] A foe to tyrants, and my country's friend;
[00:29.51] I am the son of Marcus Cato, ho!
[00:32.90]BRUTUS And I am Brutus, Marcus Brutus, I;
[00:36.87] Brutus, my country's friend; know me for Brutus!
[00:37.64] [Exit]
[00:56.12]LUCILIUS O young and noble Cato, art thou down?
[00:59.79] Why, now thou diest as bravely as Titinius;
[01:02.79] And mayst be honour'd, being Cato's son.
[01:06.50]First Soldier Yield, or thou diest.
[01:07.47]LUCILIUS Only I yield to die:
[01:10.66] There is so much that thou wilt kill me straight;
[01:11.69] [Offering money]
[01:14.24] Kill Brutus, and be honour'd in his death.
[01:16.30]First Soldier We must not. A noble prisoner!
[01:19.36]Second Soldier Room, ho! Tell Antony, Brutus is ta'en.
[01:22.18]First Soldier I'll tell the news. Here comes the general.
[01:23.59] [Enter ANTONY]
[01:25.69] Brutus is ta'en, Brutus is ta'en, my lord.
[01:26.78]ANTONY Where is he?
[01:29.54]LUCILIUS Safe, Antony; Brutus is safe enough:
[01:32.62] I dare assure thee that no enemy
[01:34.34] Shall ever take alive the noble Brutus:
[01:38.19] The gods defend him from so great a shame!
[01:41.96] When you do find him, or alive or dead,
[01:45.61] He will be found like Brutus, like himself.
[01:48.87]ANTONY This is not Brutus, friend; but, I assure you,
[01:51.36] A prize no less in worth: keep this man safe;
[01:53.49] Give him all kindness: I had rather have
[01:54.88] Such men my friends than enemies. Go on,
[01:58.61] And see whether Brutus be alive or dead;
[02:00.12] And bring us word unto Octavius' tent
[02:01.99] How every thing is chanced.
[02:02.49] [Exeunt]
[02:03.00] ./Plays/18-Julius-Caesar/18-Julius-Caesar-Act-5-Scene-4.mp3 ./Plays/18-Julius-Caesar/18-Julius-Caesar-Act-5-Scene-4.lrc
