[00:00.51] [A street.,]
[00:01.54] [Enter CINNA the poet]
[00:08.07]CINNA THE POET I dreamt to-night that I did feast with Caesar,
[00:08.89] And things unlucky charge my fantasy:
[00:11.51] I have no will to wander forth of doors,
[00:14.80] Yet something leads me forth.
[00:19.59] [Enter Citizens]
[00:23.30]First Citizen What is your name?
[00:24.13]Second Citizen Whither are you going?
[00:25.86]Third Citizen Where do you dwell?
[00:28.55]Fourth Citizen Are you a married man or a bachelor?
[00:31.11]Second Citizen Answer every man directly.
[00:32.65]First Citizen Ay, and briefly.
[00:34.31]Fourth Citizen Ay, and wisely.
[00:37.90]Third Citizen Ay, and truly, you were best.
[00:42.43]CINNA THE POET What is my name? Whither am I going? Where do I
[00:46.86] dwell? Am I a married man or a bachelor? Then, to
[00:51.06] answer every man directly and briefly, wisely and
[00:55.43] truly: wisely I say, I am a bachelor.
[00:58.62]Second Citizen That's as much as to say, they are fools that marry:
[01:03.80] you'll bear me a bang for that, I fear. Proceed; directly.
[01:06.69]CINNA THE POET Directly, I am going to Caesar's funeral.
[01:08.80]First Citizen As a friend or an enemy?
[01:10.33]CINNA THE POET As a friend.
[01:11.74]Second Citizen That matter is answered directly.
[01:14.04]Fourth Citizen For your dwelling,--briefly.
[01:15.52]CINNA THE POET Briefly, I dwell by the Capitol.
[01:17.89]Third Citizen Your name, sir, truly.
[01:20.45]CINNA THE POET Truly, my name is Cinna.
[01:24.94]First Citizen Tear him to pieces; he's a conspirator.
[01:27.76]CINNA THE POET I am Cinna the poet, I am Cinna the poet.
[01:32.81]Fourth Citizen Tear him for his bad verses, tear him for his bad verses.
[01:34.85]CINNA THE POET I am not Cinna the conspirator.
[01:38.07]Fourth Citizen It is no matter, his name's Cinna; pluck but his
[01:39.71] name out of his heart, and turn him going.
[01:43.55]Third Citizen Tear him, tear him! Come, brands ho! fire-brands:
[01:48.80] to Brutus', to Cassius'; burn all: some to Decius'
[02:01.41] house, and some to Casca's; some to Ligarius': away, go!
[02:06.31] [Exeunt]
[02:07.00] ./Plays/18-Julius-Caesar/18-Julius-Caesar-Act-3-Scene-3.mp3 ./Plays/18-Julius-Caesar/18-Julius-Caesar-Act-3-Scene-3.lrc
