[00:00.43] [Camp near Sardis. Before BRUTUS's tent.,]
[00:06.21] [Drum. Enter BRUTUS, LUCILIUS, LUCIUS, and
[00:08.95] + Soldiers; TITINIUS and PINDARUS meeting them]
[00:10.50]BRUTUS Stand, ho!
[00:34.69]LUCILIUS Give the word, ho! and stand.
[00:37.45]BRUTUS What now, Lucilius! is Cassius near?
[00:40.14]LUCILIUS He is at hand; and Pindarus is come
[00:42.31] To do you salutation from his master.
[00:46.67]BRUTUS He greets me well. Your master, Pindarus,
[00:49.49] In his own change, or by ill officers,
[00:51.79] Hath given me some worthy cause to wish
[00:55.63] Things done, undone: but, if he be at hand,
[00:58.06] I shall be satisfied.
[00:59.66]PINDARUS I do not doubt
[01:01.06] But that my noble master will appear
[01:02.65] Such as he is, full of regard and honour.
[01:05.15]BRUTUS He is not doubted. A word, Lucilius;
[01:09.91] How he received you, let me be resolved.
[01:11.68]LUCILIUS With courtesy and with respect enough;
[01:14.50] But not with such familiar instances,
[01:16.60] Nor with such free and friendly conference,
[01:17.89] As he hath used of old.
[01:19.16]BRUTUS Thou hast described
[01:23.13] A hot friend cooling: ever note, Lucilius,
[01:25.13] When love begins to sicken and decay,
[01:27.24] It useth an enforced ceremony.
[01:31.07] There are no tricks in plain and simple faith;
[01:34.72] But hollow men, like horses hot at hand,
[01:36.78] Make gallant show and promise of their mettle;
[01:39.59] But when they should endure the bloody spur,
[01:43.36] They fall their crests, and, like deceitful jades,
[01:47.02] Sink in the trial. Comes his army on?
[01:49.19]LUCILIUS They mean this night in Sardis to be quarter'd;
[01:51.95] The greater part, the horse in general,
[01:53.16] Are come with Cassius.
[01:54.44]BRUTUS Hark! he is arrived.
[01:56.48] [Low march within]
[01:57.76] March gently on to meet him.
[01:59.24] [Enter CASSIUS and his powers]
[02:00.39]CASSIUS Stand, ho!
[02:02.38]BRUTUS Stand, ho! Speak the word along.
[02:03.66]First Soldier Stand!
[02:04.68]Second Soldier Stand!
[02:05.70]Third Soldier Stand!
[02:08.78]CASSIUS Most noble brother, you have done me wrong.
[02:12.81]BRUTUS Judge me, you gods! wrong I mine enemies?
[02:15.61] And, if not so, how should I wrong a brother?
[02:18.31]CASSIUS Brutus, this sober form of yours hides wrongs;
[02:20.37] And when you do them--
[02:22.02]BRUTUS Cassius, be content.
[02:24.77] Speak your griefs softly: I do know you well.
[02:27.66] Before the eyes of both our armies here,
[02:29.50] Which should perceive nothing but love from us,
[02:32.52] Let us not wrangle: bid them move away;
[02:34.62] Then in my tent, Cassius, enlarge your griefs,
[02:36.81] And I will give you audience.
[02:37.90]CASSIUS Pindarus,
[02:41.80] Bid our commanders lead their charges off
[02:42.62] A little from this ground.
[02:44.43]BRUTUS Lucilius, do you the like; and let no man
[02:46.09] Come to our tent till we have done our conference.
[02:49.09] Let Lucius and Titinius guard our door.
[02:51.20] [Exeunt]
[02:52.00] ./Plays/18-Julius-Caesar/18-Julius-Caesar-Act-4-Scene-2.mp3 ./Plays/18-Julius-Caesar/18-Julius-Caesar-Act-4-Scene-2.lrc
