[00:08.89] [The same. The field of battle.,]
[00:09.68] [Alarum. Enter BRUTUS and MESSALA]
[00:16.14]BRUTUS Ride, ride, Messala, ride, and give these bills
[00:18.57] Unto the legions on the other side.
[00:24.39] [Loud alarum]
[00:32.84] Let them set on at once; for I perceive
[00:35.58] But cold demeanor in Octavius' wing,
[00:38.34] And sudden push gives them the overthrow.
[00:44.67] Ride, ride, Messala: let them all come down.
[00:49.67] [Exeunt]
[00:56.00] ./Plays/18-Julius-Caesar/18-Julius-Caesar-Act-5-Scene-2.mp3 ./Plays/18-Julius-Caesar/18-Julius-Caesar-Act-5-Scene-2.lrc
